Inventory of the Roman Zambrowski papers, 1948-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
Roman Zambrowski papers, 1948-1977
2003C40
Zambrowski, Roman, 1909-1977
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, other writings, diaries, and printed matter, relating to political conditions in Poland and to the Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza.
Related Materials
Antoni Zambrowski Collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2003.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1909 Born in Warsaw as Rubin Nusbaum
1928-1939 member, Polish Communist Party
1930-1938 member, Communist Association of Polish Youth Central Committee
1943 organizer, Union of Polish Patriots
1944 member, Polish Communist Central Bureau
1944-1947 deputy, State National Council
1944-1964 member, Polish Workers' Party, and Polish United Workers' Party and Central Committee
1947-1952 vice-marshal, Sejm (Parliament)
1948-1954, 1956-1963 secretary, Central Committee
1963-1968 vice-president, Supreme Chamber of Control
1968 removed from all government positions
1977 dies in Warsaw
Scope and Content of Collection
Diaries,memoirs, other writings and photographs, relating to political conditions in Poland, especially after 1945 and to the Polish communist movement and Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza; Poland-Politics and government, 1945-1980; Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza; Communism--Poland--History; Communism--Europe, Eastern
Collection Contents
- Diaries, 1969-1971.; 1 (Box 1:)
  Typescripts and holographs. Arranged by physical form.
  - Typescripts, 1969-1971 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Holographs, 1969-1971 (Folder 1: 2)
- Memoirs, 1955-1977; 1 (Box 1: 2)
  Typescripts and holographs. Arranged by physical form
  - Typescript, Parts 1-2, 1977 (Folder 1: 3-4)
  - Holograph, 1955-1973 (Folder 1: 5)
- Writings, 1975-1977; 1-2 (Box 1-2: 5)
  Typescripts. Arranged in alphabetical order
  - Czerwona ksiega PRL. Starzy komunisci o polityce PZPR. Typescript, 1978 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Listy do wladz partyjnych. Typescript, 1977 (Folder 2: 1)
  - KPP a Centrolew. Typescript. Two copies, 1976 (Folder 2: 2-3)
  - Szkice z dziejow KPP. Typescript. Two copies, 1978 (Folder 2: 4-5)
  - Uwagi o wojnie polsko-radzieckiej 1920. Typescript, 1975 (Folder 2: 6)
- Printed matter. Stosunki niemiecko-radzieckie w latach 1939-1941. Dokumenty z archiwow niemieckiego Ministerstwa Spraw Zagranicznych. Departament Stanu, 1948. Wydawnictwo Ministerstwa Spraw Zagranicznych, 2 (Box 2: 6)
  Arranged by volume number
  - Volume 1, 1948 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Volume 3, 1948 (Folder 2: 8)